[Music]
and we are live hello and welcome to the
asket show I hope you're all doing very
well thank you so much for being here
with me online tonight today wherever
you are today tonight doesn't matter so
before we begin as always let's take a
look at who all is there
on the live chat I can see Shaker once
again shakar M minalin akiles aluminati
Creek Rahul anurag Vishnu mohanan Sami
Jane Sunil seel YK J diit Captain cool
anit Chri vinyas threat
Ripper chandana Mund Omer hello bunny
red
GNA showcased K Arpita
tanay dibaba flick edits Supra internet
Alpha Prat feminist Slayer Jin venkatesh
Krishnan assri Vladimir
zalinski pray Kumar geopolitical toan
Chri rindra zubon isong shakar Manish
Ashish Prashant mitun gorov soat dianu
Ray shivakumar supria John Wick Mr
morius wasi
makram badri Vishal tanay Pand Tas hello
T aam bori Lance log Eddie wandering
monk Rohit Sharma AR deab siiva ramak
Krishna Jil Jil hamti Alpha anul Sharma
mukund
Anar unknown Desh premy harid borya
hello K Universal Pro jitu chetri J BJ s
namaste Falcon anit Captain cool and
everybody else I can go on forever but
yeah let me end here I will not be able
to greet you all individually but thank
you so much for being on this live
stream before we begin uh let me once
again for those who don't know let me
tell you that I have created a course on
geopolitics many many of you have been
asking me the past two years to create a
course on geopolitics so I have created
that the link is in the description the
link is ac. University very simple very
straightforward check it out only for
ious people who are really interested in
understanding geopolitics go for it if
you are interested all right with that
said let us go for the questions and I
can see lots of questions coming
in all right so let's take some um
questions let's take uh the first one by
Muhammad yakub Khan what's your view on
racism against Indian laborers by local
local Taiwanese and their
ministers look we have to understand
that India has historically the last I
don't know what 100 years being an
extremely poor country okay extremely
poor country destroyed devastated by the
British in 1947 when they left finally
India's GDP was like abysmal less than I
don't know less than 1% of the world's
GDP and India's life expectancy was what
30 31 something like that horribly
devastated country okay and nobody
respects those who are poor no one likes
them because you know you're afraid that
they'll come and ask for something give
me some money give me something other so
historically the past 100 or so years
people have had this very negative
opinion of Indians for nation that is
mired in poverty nation that is mired in
dekay and and all that and after 47 all
the way to 2014 there was no progress
there was no progress India remained
mired in socialism and India remained
mired in poverty the great election
slogan used to be Roti Kapa
makan Roti Kapa makan basics Basics just
to stay alive so that's why people have
and and these lingering Notions these
lingering Impressions will not it it
will take time for these Notions and
these Impressions to go to to
change India in the past decade has
changed tremendously I would say since
91 there's been progress but the past
decade we have solidified it in into
policies that take the country forward
so despite India now progressing despite
India now genuinely being recognized as
a major world power and so on it will
take time for these attitudes these
Notions these Impressions these beliefs
about India to change it'll take time uh
so and the fact is that there is racism
in every country okay there is racism
everywhere in every country no country
is exempt from it there there could be
some in India as well I'm not talking
let's not talk about that that is not
part of the question but every country
has racism Every Nation believes the
people of every nation believe that they
are the best and everybody else is an
outsider and you know not good enough
and all that so and and the
Chinese over the past 150 or 200 years
have developed a certain kind of
perception of India a nation that is
essentially a vasal a puppet of the
western powers and that that began due
to the participation of certain Indians
in the Opium Wars in the middle of the
in the middle of the 19th century in and
in the Opium Wars the British were you
know they were extracting concession
from China they were you know they had
occupied Beijing they had done all kinds
of terrible atrocities they had
introduced foreign religions into China
forcibly uh and they used Indian labor
Indian
soldiers okay it was probably Indian
soldiers that took part in many of these
activities that the British uh did in
China so the impression of Indians kind
of went down from that time on onwards
in China the Taiwanese are Chinese so
it's it's all of that so there's going
to be racism Indians these days the
Indians face in face increased racism
not just in Taiwan locally one one place
but if you look at social media which I
do from time to time you will see a
tremendous outpouring of racism against
Indians they've coined certain terms for
Indians and all that and so so on
and they especially in the west they
they seek to downplay anything India
does and and disparage India and that's
because India is finally rising and they
don't like it you know what's the term
stay in your L stay in your lane don't
get off the reservation these are
American terms so you know they feel
threatened and insecure because of
India's new you know new found strength
and India's continuing rise so it's
natur natural for these reactions to to
occur and it's actually good it tells
you India is doing something right or
many things right and people are feeling
insecure and uh you know they're feeling
insecure about it and they're feeling
threatened by India's rise that India
will eventually you know take over some
of the glory that we had and that sort
of thing so I think it's just a natural
process the world is like an ecosystem
like a forest and uh you have you know
imagine an aquarium fish tank with lots
of different kinds of fish in there and
the fish will all be cooperating and
competing against each other big fish
want to eat the small fish the small
fish want to eat smaller fish certain
kinds of fish will band together so that
together they have some kind of strength
against a big bigger fish and all that
so that's just how it is and when some a
small fish starts getting big there's
going to be push back from the other
fish so that's just how it is these
racist attitudes they obviously you
you'll see more of that in certain
countries and less in some countries but
I think it's just something we have to
take in our stride uh let's not keep uh
you know take our eyes off the ball keep
playing the ball forget about the noise
the chatter the the sledging that comes
around from the opposition players keep
your eye on the ball and show them who's
the best all right so yeah good question
good question to start off
with Okay so Jan says if Europeans are
descendants of yam then why do most
Indians not have blue eyes unlike
Europeans well uh see first of all we're
not entirely sure what's the origin of
the amn if you look at genetic genetics
research that you see today the yam
where they like map map we need the map
when we talk about stuff like this we
have to put the map on the screen I
think it's a male thing I believe you
know it's a male thing to be obsessed
with maps well whatever so the yam
according to current prevalent genetics
research originated somewhere in Central
Asia the Stan region kazakistan
usbekistan turkistan all that region
okay and
uh and maybe the origin of the Indo
European languages was somewhere in the
what do they call it the the the
Southern Crescent or something which so
initially the Arians used to used to it
was believed that they originated in
Eastern Europe now it is Iran and so on
so these you know these This research as
as more and more data emerges as more
and more research is done these things
will keep changing and eventually
someday maybe we'll find out where what
the origins are but yes the origins of
the European people most of them uh the
ones who have the r1b Hao group the R2
Hao group all that the origins are very
much yam Origins now this term yamaya it
comes from the Russian word yamna which
means a pit a pit a hole in the ground
so those people who are called who we
call yamaya today they did not call
themselves yamn we don't know what they
call themselves we have no idea what
what designation they had for themselves
we in India call ourselves bhattia or
Indian in Fran France they call
themselves Leon the French and so on we
don't know the Russians call themselves
The Rose and so on these people who we
call Yam we don't know what they call
themselves you don't know what language
they spoke but it is believed that they
would have spoken an Indo European
language they were reasonably tall
strong people roughly 510 511 height
strongly built strong bones horse riders
they should drink milk and all and they
rampaged across Europe they just you
know wiped out the native European male
populations not the female population
male populations because they were all
males so definitely it is very clear now
that this happened around 4,000 500
years before today a sudden ridiculously
rapid Invasion by these people from the
East and these people like I said they
were 51 511 tall on average they were
the males they had strong bones they had
this diet based on Dairy and they had
brown eyes and light light brown skin
and dark hair okay that's how they were
now we are not sure for now we cannot
conclude or we cannot claim that they
were of Indian origin and there's also
yam component to some extent in
India and the yam like I said at that
time they had dark hair light brown skin
they were not white people they did not
have white
skin okay and probably did not have blue
eyes probably this blue this genetic
mutation for blonde hair and blue eyes
it it occurred somewhere in I think
Western India or the Middle East and
then it spread across in the West in the
west uh So This research is in progress
uh the
Europeans not all Europeans are
descendants of yam by the way the Celtic
peoples probably were so yeah all the
Europeans aren't descendants of Y but
it's in northern and western Europe that
you will see this yam very strong
presence of yam
ancestry now why do Indians not have
blue eyes because we are we haven't
imported those genetics to a large
I could revisit that so yeah that is the
deal is India going towards
dictatorship okay let us Define what
dictatorship
means dictatorship means rulle by well
nominally one person but it means this
see a
dictator he it's typically a he you can
have she also but let's say it's a he
okay a DI dictator can never rule alone
there's a whole administrative
Foundation that this person needs he
needs an inner circle of officers or or
you know minions
minions there there needs to be a very
large Outer Circle of Administrators all
of that is is a it's it's a system and
this person is the head and that person
has somehow maneuvered himself to that
position that's typically what a
dictatorship is and in a dictatorship
you have just one person who is the
ruler there are no elections if
elections happen those are fake
elections there are many countries where
fake elections happen by the way okay
you you conduct I mean in North North
Korea is the stereotypical dictatorship
there's just one family that has ruled
the past I don't know since the Korean
war ended yeah 50s it was Kim ilung then
Kim Jong then Kim Jong Il then Kim Jong
Un so so this guy Kim Jong-un Shri Kim
Jong-un G is the third uh uh member of
the dynasty the Kim Dynasty so this is
the stereotypical dictatorship they have
elections they have elections and Mr Kim
typically wins 99.98% of the vote and
that's how it is and that those that
0.02% uh whoever is responsible for that
not good for them so even in a
dictatorship you can have elections but
it is one party and one person at the
top and that person has a personality
cult everybody there are statute of that
person everywhere everybody bows down
when the person appears you to show you
know you have to show your intense
happiness and Cry tears of joy when when
when when a member of the dynasty dies
you have to mour and tear out your hair
and seven days of mouring everybody
wears black that's what a dictatorship
is and it is an authoritarian State a
dictatorship uh people don't have a
voice a certain opinions are
strongly not discouraged but completely
not allowed and there is and there
typically are concentration camps often
and so on okay and no descent is allowed
nobody dare say a word against the ruler
that's a dictatorship now take a look at
India you see a barrage of abuse online
on social media on YouTube on Twitter on
Facebook you see a barrage of abuse and
criticism against Prime Minister Modi
every single day do you call that a
dictatorship
I mean if there was a real dictator in
place in India a real dictator nobody
would dare say a
word okay so that's not a dictatorship
and once again in India you have like
789 political parties that number could
be less actually more actually I could
be my my that figure that I just gave
out could be very low actually so there
could be more there could be thousands
of political parties in India every sing
Single city has a political party of its
own every state has like 17 18 different
Regional parties every single religion
has like 18 political parties for it
special interest groups and all it's a
chaotic democracy that's what we have in
India there is no consolidation
centralization of power so India is not
going towards a dictatorship despite
what whoever may be saying I don't know
who it is I don't keep track of what
people say but yeah that's the
deal
uh tanai Pand says this government's
policy against China is weak year byye
trade deficit is incre increasing look
you can't control the global economy you
need to import certain things at all uh
what India see there are certain things
India needs to do Visa V China trade of
course yeah if there's a trade deficit
they benefit from it and they can use
that against you essentially they can
fund your enemies they can use that to
construct infrastructure against you and
so on so forth I'm sure there will be uh
steps that will be Tak taken longterm
see these issues are long-standing
issues you can't resolve them overnight
of course this government has been in
power for 10 years that is true uh but
certain certain problems I think they
take longer to resolve what India really
needs to do is to have an effective set
of deterrence against the Chinese the
real problem is with the Chinese economy
India's economy is also Rising it's
rising now faster than China China's
economy China's economy has had a 20
year 25 year 30 year Head Start we
started late so it's going to take time
for us to grow larger is an economy it's
it's a game of patience it's we we to we
to be we are in this for the long term
long whole uh what what India really
needs to do against China is to have a
set of policies non-negotiables that we
need to implement one of the things is
that we need to significantly bolster
our military capabilities that only
happens if your GDP Rises because the
more the larger your economy is the
larger your GDP is the more you can
spend on Military uh expenditure so the
GDP needs to rise the Indian economy
needs to rise for 20 years minimum at a
at a reasonable rate 7 8% 6 7 8% uh
correspondingly the the military
expenditure needs to rise India must
maintain a very effective nuclear
deterrent Visa V China and we are doing
that the ug5 MV missile test in case you
don't know what it is check out my video
on that in which I've explained what
that is so that is a very potent
deterrent against China the the an5 can
cover all of China and more and it has
MV capabilities which means we can
release multiple Miss multiple Warheads
from one missile and these can all be
targeted independently of each other and
so on so there's a set of things India
must do and those are the more critical
things because China is an existential
threat you know you could say that so
that's what India needs to do apart from
that we can cooperate with China in
certain things as far as benefits us as
well so I would not say that this
government's policy against China is
weak there are lots of compulsions that
we the public may not be aware
of okay we have access to some data and
and lots of opinions of some great uh
influencers there are things the
government knows and is aware of that we
are not supposed to know and based on
all that the government will take the
best decisions for the country that's
what it go that's I mean this government
at least does that past governments one
would not be very sure about so I would
disagree with you Tay that this
government's policy against China is
weak yes we we have a trade deficit that
is something that needs to be tackled
but the world is not only about trade if
you see my course on geopolitics you
will realize that hard power econom the
the GDP is just one component of hard
power we tend to look at Global rankings
you know Power Rankings the we we tend
to look at the strength of Nations
purely based on
GDP well that is a very naive and overs
simplistic approach there is so much
more that goes into a nation's hard
power so we need to have a more holistic
look at what is it that goes into
constructing the hard power scoree of a
Nation so that's yeah if you're
interested that's that's covered in my
course all right let's take some more
questions red says are the Turkish
people turkified Greeks since they are
genetically similar or closer to the
Greeks Southern Italians and Southern
Europeans absolutely
absolutely so let's talk about turkey
this nation turkey they call it shall we
use the map let us use the map all right
I hope we all know where turkey is we
know where India is go westwards there
is a temporary Nation there is Iran
there's Iraq Syria and then turkey
turkey this nation here so today you go
to this place they speak Turkish they
practice a Turkish version of the
religion of the Arabs the the Islamic
religion
and uh yeah so it's a and the culture is
turky or Turkish culture now how did the
Turks end up in this region because
historically this was Anatolia it was a
Greek region Greeks and Armenians and
Georgians lived here there were not
Turks there so what happened so this all
happened in the late
1200s was it no sorry early 1200s early
1200s the first quarter of the 13th
century so at that time our dear friends
the Turks they they used to live on the
edges of the GOI desert and they used to
live in various parts of Central Asia
all right the kazakistan usbekistan
turkistan kirgistan Tajikistan all that
that not Tajikistan but other parts of
Central
Asia now what happened is that a sudden
force of nature erupted out of Mongolia
it was the great uh you know Freedom
Fighter Shri chingis Khan and he decided
to invade the Empire of quaz
which was based out of Iran and
turkistan at the time this was a turkic
Empire it was the Turks who were ruling
Iran at the time now chingis Khan did
this in retaliation for atrocities
committed by the quarians against
Mongols so chingis Khan comes out of
Mongolia he goes westwards and these
Turks who are living in Central Asia
they run for their lives they run for
their lives because they know this this
is a force of n nature that they cannot
handle the Mongols
so what they do is they run westwards
they run they escape westwards and
eventually from the Caucasus region they
make their way into
Anatolia and in Anatolia you had
very you know harmless people more or
less I mean they must have fought to
some extent but they were very easily
conquered uh and at that time what we
call Anatolia was you had the Byzantine
Empire in parts of Anatolia so there was
a long period of the Turks fighting the
byzantines the Byzantine Empire was the
Eastern Roman Empire and eventually the
Turks were able to conquer and destroy
the Byzantine Empire and then they took
over they essentially took over what was
left of byzantin Empire and their
Capital was Constantinople now called
Istanbul now the Turks were small in
Number the population of Anatolia and th
which is like Western the European part
of turkey all of that that was much
larger so what the Turks would do they
had this custom called bride
kidnapping in which you just go and
capture whatever girl woman you want and
you force that girl to marry you and
they did this for Generations they're
still doing that in Cyprus so Northern
Cyprus is under Turkish occupation okay
since the 1970s and they are doing that
to Greek women even now in Cyprus so
that's the deal so over time over
several Generations the Turks
there was hardly any turkic component
left in the
Turks and if you look at the genetics of
the Turks today you will find there
there's almost nothing from Central Asia
in there it's all uh Anatolia Greek the
anatolians were mainly Greeks and
Armenians and Georgians to some extent
uh yeah so their genetics are much
closer like you say to the Greeks the
southern Italians and the southern
Europeans so they are very much
turkified Greek
but most of them would be very offended
if you said that despite the genetic
evidence that's all around the place now
but that's just what it is there will be
some Trace Central Asian turkic
component left in most people some
people may have a little more but most
of them have very little of it or if
none maybe some of them have none of it
uh so yeah that is that is indeed true
the Turks are turkified the Turkish
people are turkified
Greeks
all
right what else do we
have sound guy abishek varu says does
the Brain Store audible data when we
sleep I fell asleep listening to a
podcast with headphones Z next day I
sense the every moment every minute I
replayed it so we don't know uh
Neuroscience neurology all of that is a
big mystery we know what the brain looks
like uh when you go to medical school
you get to dissect brains and all that
takes slices and sections and we know
everything which is inside the brain the
various components the pawns the M
oblongata the various whatever
components we have of the brain but we
don't know how they function we know at
a microscopic level how neurons connect
with each other and that's how they form
memories we know how they communicate
through with electrical impulses and
signals through ions calciums sodium
whatever it is I don't remember now it's
been too long and so on so we know how
neurons communicate with each other how
memories seem to be formed we know what
the different components of the brain
are the frontal frontal lobe and
whatever else we know how the the the
eyes are actually an extension of the
brain okay they are the light Gathering
device and they are directly connected
to the brain so if you squeeze your eyes
like that it's going to kind of end up
squeezing your brain but
Nature has we have adapted and evolved
to that in such a way that it doesn't
really hurt the brain harm the brain the
point is we don't know how various kinds
of data are stored in the brain we know
where sound auditory data is stored in
what part of the brain we know where
Optical data is stored in what part of
the brain we know that you can even
disconnect two parts of the brain for
whatever reason and then you will have
two split personalities of of sorts and
so on the point is we don't know how
this works and what happens so when we
are asleep what happens I think we we uh
are not quite connected to the end to
the world unless there a big noise or
some big flash or something then that
may wake us up but otherwise we kind of
oblivious to what's happening outside
but and yet and yet it is possible that
these uh sounds that are being piped
into the ears through your headphones
they may have some effect and some
memories may be formed we don't know but
it is is possible it is not out of the
question so we don't have definitive
answers but the possibility does indeed
exist okay
um abiraj K says K says what do you say
about Isis comment for bat so I've heard
they made some comment I have not seen
the comment uh once again let's go to
the map because you if you want to
understand what the deal is so these
fellows they are called
Isis koras Province krasan krasan
Province so karasan comes from the term
quasm the old term karazma which was the
turkey Kingdom that chis Khan invaded
and
obliterated so karasan is this region
essentially Iran Afghanistan Central
Asia turkistan Tajikistan that sort of
thing and uh this Isis Cas is kind of
based on of this area so Northwest of
India Afghanistan and Tajikistan maybe
Turkmenistan usbekistan that sort of
thing definitely not Iran and one of
their stated
targets officially stated targets is
India okay and they see India is
obviously a unfriendly nation and they
have also apparently taken credit credit
for the recent terrorist attack in
Moscow but I don't think that is that is
the case because it looks like a fake
clip so I don't know what comment they
have made but the point is that India
needs to be very much aware of this
threat any terrorist organization that
has uh that exists in the vicinity in
the larger uh surrounding area of India
whether it has stated it's made any
threat or not India needs to be careful
about that and India needs to track
those activities very carefully and I'm
sure that India is doing that so that is
what I can say about this
matter kirumi kirumi says ancient
connection and Brotherhood between India
and Iran could have been one of the
reasons India didn't expand and Conquer
repeatedly in Central Asia even though
we could have Indians did conquer
Central Asia parts of Central Asia one
example is keska now some people would
say keska was a kusan he came from
somewhere else do you know how much he
did for Indian culture and how much he
did to safeguard India's national
interest keska was very much Indian 100%
200% like 10,000% Indian more Indian
than certain other Emperors that people
like to defy and worship jalaludin Akbar
zahin Babar you call those guys Indians
yeah keshka was Indian now keska once
again let's go to the map I don't know
why I love the map so keska conquered
much so his his kingdom it touched the
shores of the Caspian and the Aral the
Aral is now more or less dis appeared
but you can see the Caspian Sea is it's
north of tan this is the Caspian Sea so
kanishka's Empire touched the shores of
the Caspian Sea and the Aral Sea and he
also conquered what is today Tibet in
shinjang all the way to the tarim River
Basin okay today's uh what's it called
taklamakan desert all of that was
conquered by Shri kanishka so that's one
example then you had I think kumara
Gupta from the Gupta Empire who
conquered balik
who defeated balik and turned them into
a wasal state balik is bul which is
present day Afghanistan Turkmenistan
that
region so Afghanistan of course it's
it's a part of the subcontinent but yeah
today some people consider Afghanistan
to be part of Central Asia which I would
not agree with but yes so kumaragupta
did Venture into Central Asia not far
beyond Gandhara but to some extent he
did then you had ladya mapa who
conquered large parts of Central Asia
right so Central Asia wasn't
Iranian Central Asia was Indo Iranian
you had the Shaka people living there
the the skians the skians were Indo
Iranian when they came and conquered
India around
2,100 years ago they had the same
culture as the Indians there was no
clash between the Indians and the skians
they harmoniously integrated into Indian
Society it is only after the Turks
rampaged across Central Asia that the
genetics and the culture changed in
Central Asia today if you look at
Central Asia it's tur all these Tans
kazakistan usbekistan turkistan
kyrgistan these are turkic
nations the people in this Nations will
be like a mixture of ethnicities half
turkic half old skan so and maybe more
skan maybe more turkic or maybe the male
genetic lineage will be tkic and the
female genetic lineage could be uh skum
that sort of thing the UR are a classic
example some of them look very Indian
some of them look very turkic and so on
so so India did conquer Central Asia at
various points in time it has nothing to
do with Iran India and Iran have never
fought a war until that Barbarian nadir
sha invaded India uh about 300 years ago
roughly I don't remember the date you
can look it up nadish sha was not
Iranian by the way he was not Persian he
was a Turk once again he was a Turk who
was ruling Iran the Iranians the
Persians have never ever fought with
India and India has never ever fought
with Persia never ever happened
remember the days I mean in case you
know of the Ain Dynasty the Akin the hak
Manish Dynasty which ruled about two and
a half thousand years ago some of their
great kings were d d dasas uh kurush
that they call
Cyrus uh who else did we
have uh arak chatra ARA xerus and so on
great Kings they had they all fought the
Greeks and the Romans they never fought
India they were expansionist
militaristic Emperors Kings they never
ever thought to fight India they always
went westwards why that is the old uh
relationship between India and
Iran okay that is the ancient connection
that is the Brotherhood and when the
Iranians finally the Persians finally
fell to the Arabic invasions they wished
that India would come to the to the
rescue but at that time India also was
not in a great shape India was not
unified politically after the fall of
the Gupta Empire and so did not work out
so to recap this doesn't the fact that
India first of all India did repeatedly
multiple times conquer parts of Central
Asia sometimes more sometimes less and
uh it had nothing to do with Iran but
yes it's a good way of thinking to try
and understand cause and effect so
overall it's a great
question
okay
um sh says when will the Indian Air
Force get its fifth generation fighter
aircraft don't you think it's quite late
um the first fifth generation fighter
aircraft that I can think of was the F22
Raptor the American plane it's a great
plane I think it's better than the
F35 so there's the F22 Raptor which kind
of is on par with 4.5 generation
aircraft today but it's considered to be
a fifth generation aircraft then you
have the f 35 then you have what else
the Chinese have a knockoff of the F22
which they call the J something it's a
complete copy of the of the F22 which
they acquired they acquired the
blueprints through hacking through this
operation in the early 2000s late '90s
early 2000s the operation the Americans
called it operation Titan rain which was
a massive Chinese hacking effort so the
Chinese acquired blueprints detailed
blueprints of the F22 Raptor and then
they constructed the J whatever J
something J I don't remember what what
number it is J something which is a
complete knockoff an inferior knockoff
of the F22 Raptor so there are certain
several Nations that uh have what's
called fifth generation fighter aircraft
typically these aircraft have have
stealth capabilities and so on so the
question is when will the Indian Air
Force get a fifth generation fighter
aircraft so we are developing the the
amca I believe that's the one that will
be the fifth generation fighter aircraft
sometime in the 2030s could be
operational I think the first flight
could be around 2029 2030 or some uh
something like that I could be mistaken
I'm not keeping track of this okay but
uh if it is indeed induct it will be
inducted not if but when it is inducted
it will be in the early the first half
of the 2030s so you know the thing is
this fighter plane development is a long
drawn out process look at the the
development life cycle of the
F35 it's taken so many decades every
fighter plane has a whole life cycle and
then the first prototype rolls out then
it may work or not work then you make a
second prototype third prototype then
you eventually induct the fighter which
is just the fighter plane into the Armed
Forces in small numbers but that is just
the first version then you have to
create a version two version three so it
takes time and then lots of versions
happen and eventually you can kind of
perfect it it's a long process so it'll
be great if India can have this fighter
plane this amca by the 2030s early 2030s
uh yeah so it takes time by the time we
should obviously work on the
tages we have Mark 1 a which is just
rolled out now you'll have the thees 2
as
well I'm not sure what if it's called
the thees 2 or whatever it's called but
it's going to be superior version of of
thees compared to what we have today so
it's it's a process we had a great
fighter plane in the 1960s it was called
the marut if we had not discontinued
that we would have had several families
of fighter planes based on that but we
need disc discontinued that the
wonderful whoever it was the Prime
Minister and government of India at the
time they decided to discontinue that
fighter plane so now we are in the
situation it takes time the point is
this actually we are now by the way in
the 21st century we have ai we have
drones we have un unmanned
aircraft and you know these autonomous
AI equipped unmanned aircraft can do way
more damage than a fifth generation
fighter plane so I think by the 2030s
India could also India will certainly
develop the fifth generation fighter
plane but we will also most likely pivot
in the direction of autonomous unmanned
flying aircraft or flying Fighters you
know uh if you were to compare okay how
much damage a single fifth generation
fighter plane can do compared to swarm
of drones autonomous drones I promise
you those autonomous drones can inflict
way more damage first of all they are
small they are very hard to take down
and let's say you have a swarm of 200
drones let's say the enemy takes out 150
of them okay somehow but those 50 that
are left will still do enormous damage
more than one fifth generation fighter
aircraft and these drones are
inexpensive comparatively relatively
speaking so 200 drones will cost way
less than one fifth generation fighter
aircraft that's what these wars that we
are witnessing are telling
us the arak war that happened a couple
of years ago that was when you first saw
the deadly use of loitering Munitions
suicide drones and then the the
situation in Ukraine that's showing us
how Wars will be fought in the 21st
century and how many fighter planes have
you seen in action during the
why do the Chinese deny King lad's
Conquest over China and Asia I'm not
sure if he conquered China but let's
take a look at the map all right let's
take a look at the map so l l mapa was
this king who was based out of Northern
India Shri nagar was his
capital and he was a great
conqueror in a in a short career he
conquered large parts of Central Asia he
is also said to have conquered some
parts of
Tibet but
historically historically what we see as
China today was not China let me search
for the Great Wall of
China where is the Great Wall of China
okay it's somewhere here okay we've got
a pin we got a pin so witness where the
Great Wall of China is you see it was
somewhere here let me try and find a
different map let's go to Google let's
go to Google let's do a Google search
for a Great Wall of China here's Google
our friend on the screen Great Wall of
China and we'll go to
images and we'll try and find a
map now these maps that we will find
online will not depict India's borders
correctly so please bear with me it is
not my doing but let me just show this
for illustration do you see where the
Great Wall of China is I think it's
visible now so these were this was the
border of China up here north and east
of
the and and west of the western most
extent of the wall was again the border
of China so Tibet was never part of
China sang was never part of China uh
Southern Mongolia was never part of
China and that is what we need to
understand if Lya conquered Tibet if he
conquered sing Jang it was not China at
the time all that became part of China
in the 20th
century all right so the Chinese and
obviously now it is part of China so you
you can claim so today we can claim that
conquered what was what is now part of
China the point is the Chinese have
suffered lots of invasions you know what
they say you know what the fact is the
Chinese have never succeeded have never
won a war that was fought on their
territory by
Invaders that's why they always seek to
pressurize other countries and try to
take the territory but the moment
there's a massive major invasion of
China by an external Force they always
lose uh I had a podcast with Dr Edward
lutwak couple of years ago and he's a
great geost strategist he has F he has
served in he has fought Wars okay
actually and he has written books about
the grand strategy of the Byzantine
Empire the grand strategy of the Soviet
Union and so on so forth great guy he
knows a tremendous amount of stuff and
what Dr Edward lutwak said was
that to conquer China all you need is
three guys on horse back that's what
they said and that's what's happened
repeatedly the Mongols a bunch of ragtag
tribals came and wiped out China they
flattened Beijing under the great
conqueror Shri chingis Khan uh the
warrior for peace
and so on the Japanese did that so many
other did the Shu did that the Huns did
that the British did that the Americans
did that and so on so the Chinese are
very sensitive about this matter it
hurts it hurts okay so that's why they
would seek to deny and they will claim
that no l actually paid tribute to some
Chinese thing or some some some nonsense
like that so you have to understand
there are multiple reasons why they make
this St first of all the regions that he
conquered were not part of China at the
time China was much smaller at the time
what and and secondly it hurts when you
if you're Chinese it hurts to
acknowledge the fact that somebody
conquered you so yeah that's these are
the reasons
why goow says why India doesn't raise
voice against the stolen Land by the US
Navy that you spoke
about
okay so let us once again go to open up
the map what is this
place that I spoke
about so I spoke about the shago the CH
the chagos archipelago the chagos
archipelago is a cluster of islands in
the Indian Ocean it's part of the lakad
chagos ridge which is an underwater
mountain range and the mountain tops the
poke out of the sea as Islands so we
know where the LX islands are here we
have the LX then you have the Maldives
and then you have the so called British
Indian Ocean
territory and this used to be
administered from morus and in 1965 the
British separated it from macius because
they wanted to give macius Independence
but they wanted to keep chigos and they
did this in contravention of UN
resolution number whatever it is you can
look it up in my video I don't remember
the resolution number right now and they
kept this territory and then they gave
the island of Diego Garcia to the
Americans and before doing that they
evicted they deported all the natives
from this place and they were shipped
off to the sells some of them and some
of them to mishes that's what happened
that's the long and short of it if you
want a detail analysis check take a look
at my video that came out like two three
days
ago so that is the thing now the the
people of chos the people of morous have
gone to the United Nations and the unit
the UN is very crystal clear about this
that the UK has no sovereignty over cha
or chos and they need to give it back to
macius ASAP and they need to allow the
natives to return but the British say
that this won't happen they don't care
about the UN they don't care about human
rights and freedom and democracy it
doesn't matter when the affected people
are not wh- skinned and so on okay and
that Island Diego Garcia is entirely
occupied and operating by the US they
have a very large you want to see why
not they have a very large major
military base here Naval Base they have
a large large airport here and massive
uh massive Port as well the port can
handle aircraft carrier submarines
destroyers all kinds of Warships and
this uh Runway is as you can see it's
pretty massive if you would like to
measure the dimensions it is 3.6 kilm
right and uh
yeah they have a pretty extensive setup
over here this is the port you can
see you can see all the various
facilities they have there and so on and
there is
more groundbased
electrooptical deep space surveillance
it's a spy station okay and so
on so this is uh what the Americans
operate
now the question is that is being raised
by go is why hasn't India raised its
voice against stolen Land by the US Navy
and the UK look it is not India's job to
go and fight
every just war and to go and poke its
nose into every issue we have to
understand one thing the fact that the
Americans have a major military base
here it's it's terrible for the local
people but from a selfish Indian
national interest perspective it is good
for us because it it keeps the Chinese
kind of at
Bay right the Americans they they
acquired this this this
island the Americans acquired this
island in 1973 do you know why it became
urgent for them to acquire it in 1973
because of the debacle in
1971 they American the Americans were on
the side of the pakistanis the
pakistanis were conducting genocide in
East Pakistan pres the Bangladesh they
were killing massive numbers of
Bangladeshi Hindus mainly and the
Americans were on the side of the
pakistanis and once the hostility
started India it was it became clear
that India could win this war they sent
the Americans sent the US USS Enterprise
the aircraft carrier with a whole task
force around it other warships as well
and the British also sent an aircraft
carrier task force so there were two
aircraft carrier task forces in the Bay
of of Bengal and the Americans would
have succeeded in arm tting India into
withdrawing from East Pakistan was it
not for the USSR the USSR sent a fleet
of nuclear submarines to face off
against the Americans in the British and
that's why the Americans had to back
off and that's why India was able to
liberate Bangladesh and break Pakistan
into two so that's why it became urgent
for the Americans to have a base from
which they could project massive
military power in the region now today
India and America are not at logger
heads and the American presence in this
region is actually good for India you
know from a selfish perspective because
it kind of counterbalances any possible
Chinese actions in the Indian Ocean
region the Chinese can't be too active
in the Indian Ocean region because of
this massive us presence over here they
have the runway can take the heaviest of
of aircraft heaviest of strategic
bombers and the port is Diego Garcia can
accommodate aircraft
carriers so from a selfish pers
perspective for India it's a good thing
of course that can be used to project
power against India as well in the
future if if need be so it's kind of
that kind of situation so India doesn't
have to raise its voice in every single
matter okay and India has officially
stated that it supports the the
government of morius it supports
macias's claim on the chos island so
India has put that on the record but
India doesn't go and fight a war you
know and raise the issue we have said it
officially that we support morus in this
matter that that morus must gain
sovereignty regain sovereignty over the
chos islands which means the UK and the
US must withdraw we have said that
officially and that
suffices
right red says how um how many languages
do you speak is it possible to learn 10
or 20 languages I know one person who
speaks 13 languages that guy's the CEO
of a of a well multi-million dollar
company so that that gentleman speaks 13
11 or 13 languages I knew a professor a
lady who spoke about 13 or 14 languages
not sure how fluent she was in all of
those languages but she was a professor
of linguistics so it's it's possible for
for for some people depending on
their I don't know level of intelligence
or whatever to learn multiple languages
how many do I speak I speak four
languages and I can understand three
four other languages to a certain extent
no I would say much more than three four
the the thing is this if you speak
certain languages you can understand a
multitude of other languages without
being able to Converse in those
languages for example if you speak
French you can understand Spanish you
can understand Italian
you can understand Portuguese and so on
if you understand English then you can
see the similarities with German and so
on uh if you understand any let's say
any Sanskrit derived language you can
understand all the other Sanskrit
derived languages to a certain extent if
you speak Hindi you can understand some
of Bengali you can understand some
assamis you can understand some marati
you can understand some whatever
else and if you if you understand Tamil
you can definitely understand parts of
Telugu some of Canada some Malayalam I
think a lot of Malayalam and so on so
the thing is that you if you understand
one language you can understand multiple
other languages that are related to it
if you understand Hindi and if you pay
attention you may understand some parts
of person as well because Hindi and
person are very closely related related
actually even PTO even
PTO so if you if you'll approach
learning languages in that manner that I
already have some vocabulary of these
languages then it becomes much easier to
learn those languages if you can make
those
connections so I think I speak four
languages uh but it's definitely
possible to learn many more I did not
bother to learn too many of
them
okay geopolitical dub says finally the
government of India is restoring the
great marand Mand and installing a
statue of samat yes I saw this news
today somewhere on social media
somewhere I think on Twitter
X that uh there's going to be a meeting
about restoring various temples in
Kashmir and certainly the great uh Surya
Mand the Maran Mand and the government
will install a statue of the great
emperor the great conqueror Shri ladya
mapa so I think it's
fantastic we are beginning the process
of
decolonization there were two kinds of
colonizations in India we think of
colonization colonialism as British
colonialism right but there was a turkey
colonization also of India and that also
needs those those scars the damage it
did need to be undone slowly in a in a
proper
manner proper legal Manner and that that
I think the process is beginning so I
think it is good uh so yes that that
great Temple lies in ruins it will be
restored I think I hope the restoration
is done well uh I'm sure it will be done
well and a statue of the the the builder
of the temple mapa will be installed
over there so that is great A very
welcome move and I am really glad that's
happening gorov Sharma says this year
NASA will send crude Mission emus too to
the moon but the crew will venture
around the moon and return why not land
on the
moon uh when you look back to the 1960s
the Apollo
missions uh the first Apollo mission was
a round trip trip around the
moon so you have to do things in
stages uh initially you just test out
the rocket it works fine or not the you
know the vehicle the launch vehicle then
you send the launch vehicle on an
uncrewed trip around the Moon to see
that it performs properly or not you go
and send it to into moon's orbit
slingshot it and return back to Earth
you don't put any crew in that so that
you see but you create but you create an
environment that would sustain a crew
with oxygen pressure and all that and
then you have instruments that will
measure all the all the all the
parameters that you know that it's
performed well so you first send an
uncrewed rocket then you send a crude
rocket with crew with human crew but you
send them on a round trip around the
Moon does a slingshot maneuver around
the moon and returns to earth not
slingshot but you know that maneuver
that figure eight maneuver one part of
the eight is small one is big and it
returns to earth and then finally when
you are completely
confident that everything performs fine
all the all the various systems
subsystems components sub components all
the everything performs nominally as
expected then you would send a crew to
actually touch down on the moon so it
has to be done phase by phase you cannot
Rush these things otherwise it could end
up in a disaster when it comes to the po
Polo program once again there was a
disaster there was a fire in one of the
launches
and it it killed three American
astronauts on the
Launchpad so they they learn from that
they they learned many lessons from that
first of all the environment inside the
capsule that contains the human crew
should not be pure oxygen and secondly
when there is and secondly the
doors of the capsule should not open in
inwards because if there is high
pressure inside then you can't pull the
door inwards and so on so if you study
the history of space flight you will you
know no notice all these different
incidents and the way sometimes very
hard and painful lessons had to be
learned so that's why this is any space
agency would be extremely cautious
extremely prudent extremely conservative
extremely careful while conducting human
space flight missions especially when
they haven't done this in decades the
last American astronauts on the moon uh
I think the landed there in the
1970s ' 7s late '70s I think early ' 80s
I don't remember exactly but I think
late '70s so it's been what how many
years 80s 90s 2000s 2010s 40 45 years
almost 50 years since they've done this
so they are essentially learning this
again from scratch so they're going to
be very careful very conservative first
send an unmanned spacecraft then send a
crew around the Moon not touchdown then
eventually touchdown on more that's how
it's going to be you have to be very
careful because human life if there is
is an incident and human lives are lost
then there's going to be big public
outcry against this and that could
damage the Pro Prospect of the space
program that's
why um let us
see YK says boing airplanes how did the
quality drop over the
years
yeah the quality of the US has dropped
over the years
the standards that they hold themselves
to as a nation the United States those
standards have dropped drastically in
the past couple of decades especially in
the past decade the past 10 years right
so if you go back to the 1950s 1960s the
Americans had the highest standards in
the world they believed in American
exceptionalism they believed that they
were truly the greatest country in the
world and they held themselves to those
high
standards right
and that's why they were able to succeed
the way they did that's why they were
able to do that now in recent times not
recent times it All Began in the 1950s
and 60s this uh infiltration of the
academic system by
leftists and they brought in new ideas
they slowly started pushing socialist
ideas and eventually the entire academic
system of the US was captured by the
Socialists the leftists the marxists
whatever you want to call them and today
and they have have successfully
indoctrinated all the students
generations of students into believing
that capitalism is bad I'm not saying
it's good I personally not think
capitalism is good but I also don't
believe that socialism is good okay but
today the there is this indoctrination
in the US they believe in socialism they
and socialism automatically brings low
standards it causes a lowering of
Standards you know the famous experiment
Professor uh in his class he says that
uh I'm going to have an exam tomorrow
test test tomorrow and I'm going to give
everybody an average score so whether
you study or not whatever scores you get
every let's say there are 100 students
in the class and everybody gets a score
from from zero to 100 I'm going to take
the average of all the scores and I'm
going to give everybody the same score
so for the first time this happens some
people studied really hard and they get
almost 100 but some people did not study
they got 40 50 and everybody got the
same score so then over time the
students who used to study really hard
they said what's the point I'm not
getting what I have earned what I've
worked for so they stopped studying so
the average score of the class dropped
over each successive test and eventually
it was near zero so that is what
socialism does if you don't get the
fruits of your labor then you stop
working hard you stop caring that's what
socialism does and that's what's
happened to the youth us so overall the
standards of the Society of the nation
have dropped
drastically even cultural standards all
of that has has gone has has dropped
very much and the same thing you will
see in in manufacturing I mean they gave
up on manufacturing cars a long time ago
Elon Musk is the only guy that's that's
uh still holding the flag all the
Detroit automobile manufacturers they
gave up to the Japanese the Japanese had
the highest standards and these guys
could not do that even the even in the
they they kind of gave up so Detroit
today is is
Wasteland and so on when it comes to
aircraft Boeing has had high standards
then they merged with McDonald Douglas I
don't remember which year it happened
and then they shifted their they moved
their headquarters from the original
boing head headquarters to the McDonald
Douglas head headquarters and then this
entire corporate culture came into place
where it was all about managing and all
that and not actually
improving and then you had all that
uh uh affirmative action kind of stuff
that came in so it's not one factor it's
a it's it's multiple factors that led to
the drop in quality of boing aircraft
and I think um one would I would rather
prefer to fly Airbus these days so these
days whenever I book a flight I check
take a look at what is the make of the
aircraft if it's an Airbus I'll travel
otherwise not so much you know because
yeah I mean doors fly out windows fly
out uh engines fall off wheels don't
function God
knows so yeah boing Bo seems to be on on
a very bad path right now and McDonald
Douglas used to be a really great
company I have flowed McDonald planes as
a kid the dc1 the DC whatever else very
nice planes very uniquely shaped planes
the wings used to be in the back of the
plane and they used to have a third
engine on top of the uh the vertical
stabilizer and all that very unique
looking planes McDonald Douglas planes I
don't think they fly anymore too many of
them but yeah it was a great company but
after they merged with boing it all went
downhill slowly slowly you don't see
decline very rapidly it takes time but
eventually it becomes bad so that's
where boing is
today um
ders sing Johan says what's the bgv
theorem by Alexander venin I haven't
heard of this let's Google it let's try
and Google it I haven't heard of this
strange I typically know
everything okay what's bgv
the bgv theorem what is
this okay B good the physical cosmology
that is that the univer that any
Universe has on average been expanding
throughout his history and cannot be
infinite in the past but must have a
past space-time boundary I wasn't aware
of
this
uh okay this is something I haven't been
involved in and I haven't really come
across so it's it's physical cosmology
it's about the evolution of the
universe uh dides that any Universe has
that has on average been expanding
throughout its history cannot be
infinite in the past but must have a
past SpaceTime boundary yeah it makes
sense obviously oh sorry okay I did not
put that on the screen I apologize for
that
uh here is the thing
yeah okay yeah the bgb the B the G so G
is involved Alan GTH okay I know the guy
G 1981 the last
great progress in theoretical physics
Alan GL G and inflationary
cosmology so G is involved but yeah I
wasn't aware of this but it makes sense
obviously any universe that has on
average been expanding throughout its
history cannot be infinite in the past
but must have a past space time boundary
okay yeah it makes sense so that's the
bgv theorem and it does make sense
logically okay PR VES says why haven't
we found other biochemistry of life like
Silicon based rather than carbon based
life here on Earth why has Evolution
favored carbon based life we don't know
the answers we have no idea why the
things why things are the way they are
you know there are so many Mysteries
when it comes to the origin of life on
the earth the
simplest microorganisms unicellular
organisms the simplest of them have DNA
and DNA is an extremely complex molecule
extremely
complex and how does something like that
evolve so our planet formed about what
4.6
4.5 billion years before today and life
seems to have emerged about 3.77 billion
years before today so it's about 0.8
billion years 0.8 0.9 billion
years of time before which life
evolved now is that enough time for for
a random soup of chemicals to produce
something as complicated as DNA and also
proteins and for all of that to assemble
into a single cell unicellular
organism it's kind of a stretch to
imagine that that could happen in that
much time because people have done these
experiments they take various uh various
elements like carbon and sulfur and and
all that and they put that in a beaker
and then then they create the entire the
what what would have been the
environment of ancient Earth with you
know electrical charges and all that and
they heat it heat up the thing and you
do that for a few days then you can see
that the amino essds emerge out out of
that so amino acids do emerge from this
and we have found amino acids even on on
uh meteorites that fell from the sky so
meteorites do seem to have amino acids
which are the building blocks of protein
but when it comes to DNA it's a
staggeringly complex
molecule and it doesn't make sense that
it could
evolve naturally spontaneously so one of
the
theories is that when the universe was
much younger see today the average
temperature of the universe is very
close to 0 Kelvin to 0 Kelvin it's
slightly higher than 0 Kelvin and that's
the C BR temperature the cosmic
microwave background radiation
temperature which is the temperature of
the average Photon from the left over
after glow of the big
bag so the temperature is very low right
now but way back in the early uh in the
in the universe's Antiquity when the
universe was much younger much smaller
it was much hotter and there was a time
when the average temperature in space in
the universe was the same temperature
that we have here on
Earth okay and the universe was much
smaller and there could have been water
see water seems to be quite abundant in
space so there was warm temperature
there was all these there were all these
various elements that are the outcome of
the death of stars like carbon Like
Oxygen like nitrogen like sulfur and so
so on so forth iron also iron is the
iron marks the death of a star and so on
so you had all these elements you had
all these chemicals you had a warm
temperature you had lots of water so
it's possible that life would have just
evolved spontaneously in
space and then as the universe got
bigger expanded and it grew colder that
life the seeds of that life just
froze in space and they hitched the ride
on various asteroids and space rocks and
all and maybe that is what seeded life
on earth that is one of the hypothesis
that that goes around it's called
panspermia so maybe the life forms that
came on Earth from the from there they
were carbon based life forms because we
don't find silicon based life forms on
the planet so there are lots of
mysteries when it comes to the origin
and evolution of life on the planet
there are lots of things we cannot simp
cannot explain at all how does something
like DNA evolved naturally something as
complicated as DNA evolve yeah so yeah
so there are many Mysteries there are
lots of questions that are unanswered
and it's a fascinating topic we don't
know why Evolution favored carbon based
life life maybe for some reason it was
carbon based here maybe somewhere else
it may be something else based we
haven't found officially any life
anywhere else apart from our planet we
are looking but we we have very crude
instruments telescopes and all that yeah
we have to go elsewhere and and set foot
somewhere so you know we can start with
the solar system you know Europa Ulus
these these
moons uh even Titan so I'm talking about
moons of Saturn and and Jupiter so there
are good candidates for life these some
of these moons so Europa has a
subsurface ocean of water well
known Enceladus also has subsurface
water it shoots out this geysers of
water into
space which tells you that there is heat
inside there is thermal activity
geothermal
activity uh and there's Titan which has
this
complex uh soup of hydrocarbons thick
soup of hydrocarbons in its atmosphere
it has methane lakes and rivers and all
very interesting environment there could
be some form of life there very cold but
there could be some form of life there
and so on so there are candidates for
candidate worlds for the existence of
Life on in our solar system we need to
possibly explore those send robotic
probes and find find out what's
happening and so on I'm sure life could
be pretty common in the universe but the
universe is so big that we cannot see in
the in our uh the the range of our
instruments isn't that great it's not
great at all it's very rudimentary very
primitive
okay um when will we find the mystery
between behind dark matter and dark
energy we don't know uh we we are busy
fiddling with string theory String
Theory this and string theory theory
that the entire us academic system when
it comes to physics is has been captured
by the spring Theory
Mafia and if you ask them
tell me one
prediction experimentally verifiable
prediction that string theory is made
they will have no answer so we' have
spent I don't know 40 50 60 years on
string theory which is the the
mainstream Theory now for trying to
unravel what gravity is for a theory of
quantum gravity but nothing has come out
of it except for very complicated and
sometimes pretty
math so as long as we keep this we
remain fixated on Spring Theory I don't
think there's going to be any
breakthrough and secondly we need
experiments that threw out new evidence
through through out new data so when we
go back to the time when the last big
revolution happened in physics which is
a century ago more than a century ago
which is when you have the birth of
quantum
mechanics starting from 1900 and then
you had the birth of Relativity first
special relativity and then general
relativity so what drove these theories
was that you had experimental data
experiments were being
done uh and that's and they gave us new
data they gave scientists new data to a
new Mysteries to
ponder and that's why and and there was
no Dogma at the
time the kind of Dogma that you we have
with string theory so there were these
conditions so we need to recreate those
conditions
uh so I think it it's going to take time
for us to crack the mystery behind dark
matter and dark energy we'll have to
understand what gravitation is gravity
gravity is the big mystery we don't
understand what gravity is general
relativity tells us things about gravity
I mean it's stupendously successful
Theory the second most successful theory
in physics after Quantum field Theory
but general relativity doesn't work at
the quantum level at the ultr
microscopic level and when it comes to
Quantum Mechanics uh there's no gravity
in that gravity doesn't exist in quantum
mechanics so these two theories they
don't work together you try to reconcile
the two together it leads to
inconsistencies and paradoxes and all
that such as the singularities that you
have in black holes a singularity is
division by zero in your mathematical
equation which obviously is unphysical
which means that your mathematical
equation is wrong which tells you that
there is a big problem in general
relativity when it comes to uh extremely
small regions of space the quantum
domain and extremely high curvature an
extremely high mass that's when you have
these Infinities and so on and dark
energy is even more
mysterious and we don't even know what
it is that matter we know it could be a
class of particles okay we know it could
be a class of particles it is some kind
of
substance it could be is unknown
particles but and particles that
interact only gravitationally so that
much we know about dark matter and we
know that it forms Hallows around
galaxies and all you have theories like
modified neutronian gravity m d and all
that seek to
explain the rotation curves of galaxies
without without the need for dark matter
but dark matter is a mainstream Theory
and it could be a class of particles
Dark Energy we don't even know what it
is we don't even know whether it is some
kind of fluid whether it is some kind of
force no idea so dark energy is the
bigger mystery but it is the thing that
is impelling the accelerating expansion
of the
universe so yeah big mystery which
should be fascinating which which is
which is great
but there are and you know
what what we see in the universe all the
stars all the galaxies all the planets
all the light that we see in the
universe it's about 4% of the mass of
the universe 96% of the mass of the
universe is dark about roughly 25%
roughly is dark matter roughly 70% is
dark energy and dark energy is this
mysterious fluid or force or whatever it
is that is causing the excess
[Music]
even 5,000 years I don't remember
exactly how old the invention of papirus
when it happened paper in India look one
thing that is quite curious and
mysterious about the sarasti Hindu era
of our history what they call the
harapan or Indus Valley Civilization one
of the curious things is that there are
so few
inscriptions with the so-called harapan
script very few of them we get some
seals with some two three characters and
and so on there's very few inscriptions
available why is
that one hypothesis that I could put
forth is that the people our ancestors
of that time they used to write on
either paper or parchment or
cloth and that obviously disintegrated
over the over the Millennia because when
it comes to this region this enormous
region that is Main in India some parts
in Pakistan there's tremendous amounts
of rainfall every year there's a rainy
season every year and uh and and it's
quite warm it's not cold it's not frozen
so these things you know organic
material disintegrates and decomposes
rapidly so maybe that's why we have not
been able to find more examples of
haraan uh script because may maybe it
was all written on on some kind of paper
or parchment or or cloth and that's why
it's not available today so that's a
hypothesis do we have evidence for it
not yet not quite so I don't know so the
answer is I don't know whether paper was
invented in India maybe it was but do we
have evidence we don't so that is simply
where we are so if you look at uh
ancient inscriptions in Sanskrit and all
they used to be written on Birch Park
Birch Birch is a a tree that's found in
the northern regions of India you go to
Northern India in the cold regions where
it snows you will find birch trees so
that bark of the birch tree was used for
you know writing
texts and you obviously also use Palm
leaves and all that so not sure about
paper as far as I know we have we don't
have evidence that paper was invented in
India but maybe we don't have
evidence
okay so yeah I says sir for Dark Matter
during Eclipse any
thoughts I don't know what kind of
sensationalist headlines these
newspapers and Publications come up with
there's some eclipse happening somewhere
in some part of the world CERN has an
instrument a very large instrument
called the large hrone collider which
accelerates protons typically to
extremely high velocities very close to
the speed of light but you can't touch
the speed of light obviously and then
these proton beams are smashed together
and you want to see what comes out of
the
debris of this explosion because you
could see you know fundamental particles
emerge from that you know fundamental
particles do emerge from that for a very
brief amount of time so that is what the
experiment is
about and maybe some kind of dark matter
clue could come out of it perhaps so
that's an ongoing experiment if this
instrument is operated when there is a
solar eclipse somewh in the world how
does it matter how is it
connected so these sensationalistic
sensation sensationalist
headlines that and and what what would
the say some ghost particle will emerge
apparently during the eclipse I don't
know what kind of unscientific nonsense
these people pedal so if you are someone
who doesn't
have a
grounding in science let's say you've
not studied science after the 10th
standard then obviously you will not
understand this and it's not your fault
you're not supposed to understand this
so and then you rely on these I mean you
will let's say you're curious about
science what's happening then you will
read these whatever news comes out and
sometimes they come up with this
ridiculous headlines that CERN is is is
trying to communicate with extra
extraterrestrials or CERN is trying to
open a portal to a different dimension
or different Universe a
wormhole and the eclipse is a special
time when these things happen
goodness no no
no so please please don't don't believe
these ridiculous claims they're all
nonsense
okay a r says geopolitical question why
is no one helping Palestine where are
the world leaders now uh one of the
questions that needs to be raised that
need to be raised is that if the
Palestinians are suffering so badly why
aren the uh Arabic Nations opening the
doors to Palestinian
refugees clearly they don't they don't
want any Palestinian
refugees now when it comes to the fact
that other nations should help Palestine
when this unfortunate sit situation
exists well the First Nations that would
should help Palestine should be the
neighboring Nations obviously Israel is
the nation that's fighting Palestine but
the neighboring Nations should send Aid
should send
relief should perhaps take Palestinian
refugees but that's not happening why is
that
so I guess the other Arabic Nations
don't like the Palestinians it's an
issue but they don't want the
Palestinians to come and set up camp in
their
Homeland that that's what it looks like
where are the world leaders now look
it's not the world leaders problem The
Americans like to claim that they are
the leader of the Free World then why
don't you go and solve the problem but
and what they they air dropped some some
supplies food supplies and all that
medicines perhaps uh but beyond that
they've done
nothing so that is how it is see at the
end of the day in geopolitics it's all
every nation is driven by its
self-interest you will say nice things
about peace and Brotherhood and dancing
around trees and all that you will
signal great amount of virtue but at the
end of the day you will be driven by
your self-interest when somebody else is
in trouble unless you are treaty bound
to help them you won't help them so that
is simply the way the world
works
okay par says excuse me China always
gets benefited by the moves of the us
over India so do you think there is any
Sino American friendship in the
background because America wants a
villain who seems to be second
USSR um well the Americans did have
indeed imposed sanctions on China the
semiconductor sanctions and other things
all that that is that Trump started a
trade War a tariff War trade barriers
tariffs and all that which has been
continued that policy has been continued
by the Democrats by Mr Biden or whoever
it is that running the government
clearly not Biden but yeah so there is
that between the US and China and there
is this military competition the Chinese
seek to retake Taiwan all that we we
know the thing right but the Americans
uh do do make some moves that would kind
of benefit China over India when it
comes to India versus China they kind of
sometimes benefit China and we have to
understand that the economies of the two
Nations the US and China are
conjoined
conjoined it is not visible from here
but the two economies are conjoined if
there's a war between the two Nations
and let's say China is destroyed which
most likely will in a war with the US I
mean China China stands no chance
against the
US when it comes to
Warfare China doesn't stand a chance not
a chance against the US now I'm going to
be releasing my index of global power
very soon but let me show you let me
show you a
preview a preview of that index of the
global
rankings so let me put that on the
screen and then hopefully it'll make
sense so I'm showing you the top 10
Nations okay this is going to be
released soon it's going to be the hard
power rankings of all nations in the
world and there's a hard power score as
you can see
so the the hard power rank one is the US
it has a hard power score of 93.3 to
this is my calculation I'm going to be
releasing this soon so the US is number
one 93.3 to is the hard power score
number two is Russia its score is
54.2 the US is a superpower Russia is a
near superpower China comes third at
15.23 do you see the difference between
China and Russia China isn't a match
even for Russia and China is in no way a
match for the us and that and if you
look at this table you will see India is
four France is five and so on Israel is
10 if you look at this table then you
will understand why the Americans are so
worried about Russia and why they have
sought to encircle Russia and why they
have sought to impose every single
possible sanction on Russia and why it
does not
worked this stable will help you
understand why the Americans considered
Russ the primary threat even though they
keep on talking about China they want to
divert the attention of the world
towards China while working on the real
threat which is
Russia right so if if if if there's a
war and if you want to understand how I
calculated all that check out my course
in which I have explained how to
calculate hard power so it's not just
GDP GDP is one component of hard power
there are lots of other
components so where was I China so China
doesn't stand a chance in a war against
the US they will be
obliterated if there's a
war uh but the US sees India also as you
can see once again let me put that back
on the screen if you look here
number number four is India now India is
just
4.91 which is like insignificant
compared to the US but India in the
future will rise and the hard power
score Will Rise by 2050 India's hard
power score could be ahead of China if
India does the right things so the US
sees India as a longterm adversary right
now India doesn't matter for the US in
terms of hard power but in terms of the
long-term potential for India India can
be a competitor to the US and they would
not like that to happen so they use
India and China to counterbalance each
other they do certain things that will
benefit China or India and they do
things will benefit India or China and
the ideal situation of the US is that
India and China go to war and smash each
other out and both problems are gone
then they can focus only on Russia that
sort of
thing and one of the way to one of the
ways
to to counterbalance both Russia and
China at the same time for the
US is to give Japan nuclear weapons and
Henry kinger said last year a few months
before he died that Japan will probably
be a nuclear weapons power in the next
five
years yeah let's see how that goes it'll
be good for India but I'm not sure it'll
be good for Japan because it won't be
Japan's choice if that
happens
okay JF P says whoops where is it JF ped
says most human beings and their stress
will revert back to Savage animalistic
Tendencies
uh look when you're under stress stress
is obviously caused by certain
things and uh it typically is a sign of
an existential threat of some kind the
threat could be immediate or the threat
could be longterm so
stress is a reaction to various kinds of
circumstances in life now if you're
talking about stress such
as
poverty malnutrition let's say you are
in a nation where everybody is below the
poverty line there are nations like this
unfortunately in the world okay you're
in a nation where you have to fight for
your next meal you don't eat three meals
a day you eat one meal a day and you
have to fight for that meal okay if you
take a nation and impoverish it that
much where people have to fight just to
exist then there will be no point they
will not worry about culture and
sophistication and
civilization that is immaterial survival
is at stake and when survival is at
stake of you and your family then you
going to go and fight and that's how you
reduce societies to very primitive to
exhibit very primitive Behavior so
that's how it happens it's just a
survival mechanism so you either fight
or die that's how it is and then if you
choose to fight then you got to go back
to fighting in any way possible your
objective is to get the meal and the
other guy is fighting for the same meal
so you got to take him out so to take
him out you're going to have to behave
in certain Fashions which are very
primitive Savage and like you say
animalistic so only prosperous societies
are
civilized the Richer you are as a
society the more civilized you
are that is one of the ways of the
world you have
it abishek samon says does Israel have a
nuclear facility in the netive desert is
that just for research or something more
or shall we look at the map since you
have asked a question about a des in
Israel
let's take a look at the map here's the
map where's the map here it is okay
let's find the nation of
Israel so it's on the eastern coast of
the Mediterranean Sea here you have isra
so now where is this
desert okay let's find the desert so let
us Orient ourselves by first finding
beer
Shiva and south of Bersa is the desert
that you are referring to the nigar
desert as you can see it's a very arid
dry land there are
some patches splashes of green around
tiberias and all but Southern Israel is
all all dry so now we found beer Shiva
let's go further south of beer Shiva and
we have this desert here the negtive
desert and let's go to this place called
diona diona diona is a nice place now
let's look around the Moa yes we find
something here it's called negative
nuclear Research
Center as you can see there's a big road
that surrounds it it's probably a
boundary a barrier a wall probably and
if you look in here you find this
wonderful little
thing it is a nuclear
reactor so it's it's a dome it's a
cooling doome of a nuclear reactor and
there could be more reactors here
certain reactors can be shaped
differently so this is clearly now it's
officially labeled as the netive nuclear
Research Center now there was a
gentleman called M vanunu his name was
Mor vanunu and he worked at this NE
nuclear Research Center and he
surreptitiously took photographs of what
was happening inside and then he reled
those photographs to the now defunct uh
News of the World
newspaper in the UK and that's how the
world came to know that Israel had
nuclear weapons and a nuclear weapons
program so there is nuclear research
that happens there there nuclear weapons
are produced there I'm not sure where
they are stored obviously they will not
let us know they will not tell us that
that information is
classified but yeah that's the deal so
there is a nuclear facility in the
negtive desert like I just showed you
and they do uh produce file material for
nuclear weapons there which would be I I
would imagine plutonium uranium is
plutonium makes more sense compared to
uranium you need less
plutonium compared to uranium to reach
critical mass which means to spark off a
nuclear chain reaction in other words a
nuclear
explosion uh so yeah that is the deal
that's what I can say it is said to be
for research but they clearly uh produce
file material for nuclear weapons or
there tus says why are there no
underwater cities if you can go into the
space think of colonizing Mars what is
stopping us going underwater for Mining
and other
needs while living underwater first of
all we humans are as as we all know not
aquatic animals we breathe oxygen we
don't have gills like sharks and other
fish do so we can't take advantage of
the oxygen that's dissolved in water in
the
oceans so for human beings to live
underwater you would need life support
systems you would need oxygen you would
need clean water not salty water like
sea water you would need fresh water
that to uh clean portable water
drinkable water you would need food so
you would have to bring in all these
supplies from the
surface and to maintain a habitat that
could support let's say a let's say 100
people you would need a reasonably large
habitat you would need a lot of air you
would need to recycle the oxygen the the
air to scrub the carbon oxide and purify
the air so you would need a tremendous
amount of investment just to create a
habitat for a 100 people and that would
be recurring investment day after day
that you have to spend money on that you
would have to build machines that can do
all these things so imagine building a
city of let's say 10,000 people which is
just a town actually 10,000 people
imagine how much work will go into
sustaining that habitat and what do you
get out of
it maybe you mind maybe you're doing
mining well you can do the same thing
with
robots you can you want to mine for for
oil and gas you can have these big rigs
oil rigs which cost a fraction of what
it would take and they do all the work
for you they drill deep under the seabed
and extract oil gas whatever they need
and if you want to mine for metals and
all you can use robotic underwater
Vehicles submarines and all that which
also happens the point is you don't need
human presence
a human presence under underwater to do
all these things you can do all this
robotically with a fraction a very small
fraction of the cost that would it would
take to maintain a habitat for a large
number of people underwater so and
obviously there's a lot of risk involved
in in maintaining a habitat if the glass
cracks for whatever reason those 100,000
people are gone so these are some of the
reasons why it's never been done and
yeah because it doesn't make sense
economically and you have other
solutions for mining
and extracting whatever
resources Anu Sharma says why is the
current US regime it seems so weak who's
actually ruling ruling I suppose ruling
the US uh it appears weak the US uh is
losing influence in the world it's not
losing its power by any means once again
let me show you the global hard power
rankings which will tell you the whole
story even though the Biden regime
appears very weak look at these rankings
and look at the hard power score of the
US 93.3 to the next is Russia
54.2 and then is China 15.23 see the
immense gap between the US and Russia
and the US and China and India is just
4.91 so the US it may appear to be weak
but that's simply because it is losing
some
to some extent influence there's a
difference between power and influence
power is the ability to command and
control and the US isn't losing that
it's it's losing influence which means
fewer people want to listen to the US
fewer people are favorably inclined to
the US fewer people trust the US fewer
people respect the us but the ability to
command and control hasn't gone anywhere
so that is power so the current regime
does seem weak obviously you have Biden
Joe Biden who obviously is not ruling
the country the guy is incapable of
taking care of himself then his vice
president is Miss Miss Kamala Harris
who isn't the smartest person in the
world let's just put it like that you
know respectfully so obviously she's
also not ruling the country so who's
ruling the country somebody is and the
policies of the US uh this this
tremendous problems in the US everything
the price this inflation everything is
expensive people can't you know can't
get married can't can't raise families
because everything is so expensive
you're just working two jobs three jobs
just to put food on food on the table
three meals a day you can't afford rent
you can't
afford you know
utilities you can't afford gas which is
petrol and so on so things are bad in
the US but who's suffering the people
are suffering the US isn't losing its
power that's the
Paradox okay so things look bad it's
it's bad for the people in the US things
life is hard these days if you are an
American citizen an ordinary average
American citizen life is hard yes and it
doesn't seem to be on the way to getting
easier anytime soon so that is true but
the US isn't losing its power it's
losing some influence Los it's losing
trust and respect in the eyes of the
world because of its overly hypocritical
Behavior one set of rules for me and you
have to abide by a different set of
rules I can do whatever I want but you
have to abide by certain things that's
hypocrisy and it's so transparent these
days so that is the deal it's losing
respect Prestige influence trust but not
power who's ruling the
US uh who's ring the US not Biden not
Miss Harris I suppose it
is um the defense establish the military
industrial complex the the oligarchs of
the US you know the the rich
billionaires and all that that entire
cabal Coalition what some people would
like to call the Deep
State probably they are the ones who
who's ruling the US I'm just guessing
speculating I don't have any information
but if you think logically that is the
answer that kind of makes sense
okay Atara says what do I think about
the attack in Moscow is there a chance
of us involvement and how can such a
great Intelligence Agency of Russia fail
to detect and stop such a massive attack
while at War you see when you're at War
you are already stretched out in various
directions you're focused on certain
things you're focused on on Ukraine you
focused on other things if you look at
the size of Russia let's go to the map
once again
where is map is map is
here okay look at the size of Russia see
how big it
is and the and and do you think it's
it's humanly possible for an
intelligence agency to be able to
monitor everything that's happening
everywhere obviously they would like to
monitor Moscow I agree I agree
uh so the point is first of all first of
all I would like to say that it
is it's it's not possible to catch all
the fish some fish will always slip
through unfortunately there is just a
statistical probability that you can't
catch all the fish in in other me in
other words you can't uh catch all
terrorists and you can't uh uncover all
terrorist plots sometimes something will
unfortunately slip through so if if
there's an attack of this magnitude in
the capital of the country obviously
it's an intelligence failure yeah so yes
the intelligence agencies will have to
take the blame and I expect certain
Heads Will Roll in in the the sense that
some people will be sacked demoted Pro
whatever so that is there but on the
other hand it's almost impossible to
catch all
the uncover all the terrorist plots now
um is there a chance of American
involvement I would say that the chance
of American involvement is nonzero but I
don't know if it is a high chance or if
the probability is high or low uh that
is anyone's
guess uh the Russians are say first of
all Isis
K horasan Province based out of
Afghanistan and Central Asia who Target
India who want would like to Target
India they claimed responsibility for
this attack and some people would say
that Isis is a creation of the US I mean
I have a book somewhere black flags
check it out if you want
to okay
so Isis came into existence miraculously
overnight when the Syrian war was going
on and they fought Syria who else was
fighting Syria the US and after Donald
Trump came to power and he cut funding
for all these things Isis disappeared
now there is Isis K inasan Province but
they are like a small faction so if Isis
K has claimed responsibility that could
be a means of diverting attention from
where the real responsibility lies and
the Russians are saying it is
Ukraine and there could be at some point
in time proper retaliation for what
happened if they indeed uncover the fact
that it was Ukraine that was behind this
and the perpetrators who have been all
captured were
tajiks if
if it is the modus operandi of of Isis
Fighters that they want to die is in in
the terrorist attack they typically use
suicide bombings or if they use guns or
whatever they ensure that they die I
mean they want martydom so these Isis
these tajic terrorists who did all this
in Moscow they did not intend to die
they had escaped they were apparently
traveling towards Ukraine so maybe the
Russians are right maybe Ukraine is
behind this and if Ukraine is behind
this it means by by logical extension it
could perhaps mean that the US could
perhaps possibly hypothetically be
behind that yeah so obviously we don't
have the intelligence that the dat
the information that the Russians have
but yeah so we can only speculate and
guess at this point in time but uh it
looks like Ukraine could be involved in
this looks like that's what the Russians
are claiming and Ukraine obviously the
Ukraine war is a proxy war between NATO
and Russia Ukraine is the proxy NATO
means the US so there could be some
connection perhaps but I cannot make a
definitive claim statement without
having all the evidence and I obviously
won't have the evidence
the omniscient being says what were the
Dark Ages was it a
myth the Dark Ages where those times was
was was a period of time in Europe where
you had uh no progress whatsoever when
you had Superstition
ignorance uh no scient no science was
allowed if you were a scientist you
would be
burnt at the stake uh there was a
tremendous amount of persecution of
women uh any woman who practiced the
pre-christian uh Arts of uh
pre-christian Traditions which
specifically meant The Healing
Arts what we would in India Call Aura
those women were branded as witches and
burned to burn life and tens of
thousands of women were burnt as witches
maybe hundreds of thousands of them men
were also burned as witches and all that
so you had this terrible time dark time
in Europe where your your entire life
was controlled by one specific
institution which was based out of
Rome and uh you could not you know there
was no Freedom there was no progress
there was poverty all around there was
no science there was no
medicine uh there was illiteracy
everywhere most people were illiterate
there was there was there was slavery in
large parts of Europe
uh when William the Duke of Normandy
conquered uh England in the year 1066
and while he was alive and while his son
while his son Henry the first was alive
after the brief reign of
Rufus uh William Rufus so at that time
at least 10% of the population at least
at least the 10 10% of the population of
England were slaves they used to wear
these metal collars copper collars
permanently and you will find skeletons
wearing that because they were buried
like that buried like that so these were
the Dark Ages extremely bad time in
Europe the absence of light no knowledge
no
education poverty illiteracy
Superstition persecution of women all of
that so it's said a number of centuries
you can look it up what what centuries
those were I can't remember but yeah was
a bad time very bad
time geopolitical du says is a
semi-presidential system like France
good for
India um I would say for India proper
presidential system would be better
because a large an enormous subcontinent
sized country like India has to be ruled
in a specific way and if you rule it in
a very decentralized manner you need
decentralization but you also need a
consolidation of power in one place so
some power the right kind of power has
to be Consolidated in one place
centralized but there needs to be
decentralization of other kinds of Power
all across the country what you call the
cooperative federalism or whatever so I
think a fully presidential system is
actually the right system for
parat
vinit sarar says where is the $45
trillion wealth looted from India right
now the GDP of the UK is a fraction of
what they looted from India listen when
you loot wealth you don't put it into
the GDP you use it to construct things
when let let's say I'm a governor in
British India and I go back to the UK
with a tremendous amount of stolen
wealth okay not 45 trillion personally
but I let's say I Ste reasonable amount
of wealth I'll go back to the UK and
construct myself a great
Mansion I'll buy
things right I'll buy
lands I'll go to other countries and buy
land maybe I'll go to North America
which was then under under Britain and
buy large amounts of land there and
build houses there so all of that wealth
was invested in this manner in this
manner and obviously it led to the rise
of certain
families banking families perhaps for
example there was this individual called
ilahu Yale who stole a great amount of
money from India he founded Yale College
which is now called Yale University some
of that money that he stole from India
would have been invested in buying that
land and all that which and he donated
the money for that college that was
money stolen out of India so over time
all that money was sunk into the Nations
and reinvested all over the
place and that is what led to the
prosperity of Europe so all the much of
the wealth of the world was stolen and
concentrated in a small number of people
less than a billion people the people of
Europe the white people and then they
went ahead and conquered the US I mean
North America South America all that the
anglos and the British the English they
conquered North America they eved the
French
eventually and uh yeah an enormous
continent they they stole and they still
occupy it and some of the money Indian
money would have gone there as well so
the money won't be liquid it won't be
flowing in the economy it will all be
invested in various parts of the
world that's how it goes so it's not
visible but it's all go into creating
the wealth that they
have okay Mo sarar says how can we
identify the fundamental particles
produced during collisions in the LHC so
we have a large list of of known
particles and we know their properties
we know what Mass they have what charge
they have what uh mass and charge
typically is is enough to know large
number of properties
so what you do is the place in the
collider where the Collision actually
happens you have a number of an array of
instruments around
that and those instruments they capture
the characteristics so when when a let's
say two cars are colliding okay two cars
two cars are colliding with no no
occupants okay it's a robotic crash we
want to see what happens so let's say
two cars each has a speed of 150 km per
hour they they'll go head on no
occupants and then you can
take uh what you can do is you can take
a high frame rate film of that let's say
2,000 frames per second so you can see
the Collision in slow motion and you can
see every component that comes out of it
similarly that's what what is done for
the LC you take snapshots through
various means you have a magnetic
instrument that see and when a charge
particle goes through a magnetic through
magnetic lines of force it Curves in a
certain direction and based on the
curvature and the speed and the mass
that you can detect you can detect what
kind of particle it is so and then you
have certain sometimes you find an
unknown particle that doesn't belong in
your particle in your list of particles
because you can deduce the mass through
these various means and this particle
has a certain mass that we don't know
any particle has that mass and that's
how they detected the hgs B on so there
are a variety of instruments that are in
place around the Collision chamber and
they examine the debris of the
collisions in a variety of different
ways and that's how we identify what
particles come out whether it is pons
whether it is electrons whether it is
neutros uh or various more exotic
particles short-lived particles s
particles and certain particles are just
short lived particles and they they they
once get disintegrated into something
else or sometimes you have antibiotic
that's produced there was the
speculation that that that micro black
holes would be produced in the LHC I
remember in 2008 2009 at that time there
this B big hoopla that the LHC will
produce micro black holes and these they
will swallow up the the
Earth and that even if it produces micro
black holes it would still not have been
a threat to the to the Earth and I had
at that time written written an article
about that so yeah so we can detect
these I detect and identify these
particles through all of these different
instruments some instruments can detect
the charge of the particle some can
detect the mass of the particle some can
detect the track what track the particle
took whether it was a straight line
whether it was a curved track and so on
So based on all of this data that we get
we can specifically identify which
particle each of these particles what
what it
is
okay romay Raj Singh says I recently had
a chat with the British national he told
me that sunak is stupid and that the UK
is better off under under the labor
party most western still still
something look everybody has an opinion
Rishi sunak is not an elected prime
minister he's a selected prime
minister it's true right he he came to
power after the uh so you had Boris
Johnson who mysteriously resigned for
some reason some some scandalous
scandalous pictures came out of him
doing something scandalous apparently so
he had to
resign then there was a lady who was
there for like three and a half hours LZ
tress was it 10 days whatever whatever
it was the the the shortest serving
prime minister of the UK and she goes
and then Rishi sunak comes to power so
clearly these are selected Prime
Ministers runak has not fought and won
an election like Boris Johnson did
but overall I suppose he's a reasonably
intelligent person and whatever policies
he is
following those policies are essentially
dictated by the US the overlord in
Western Europe and in the EU and in NATO
is the US us and UK is is very much a
vasal state of the
US it's undeniable so visible now so
whatever riak is doing is essentially
doing whatever the US wants him to do
because you cannot afford to displease
the
master and if some people find him
stupid I don't think I don't find him
stupid he's reasonably
intelligent uh but whether it's the
labor party or whatever other party the
policies are all going to be dictated by
the us the way it is in Japan doesn't
matter who's the Prime Minister certain
things never change so that's just what
it is that is the harsh re ity of life
in the
UK okay what else what
else um Arjun utar says what do you
think about the recently released movie
swatantra swatantra sarer by randip Huda
I haven't seen it yet but I do want to
see it if I can find some time I would
like to spend how long is the movie to
three three hours I don't know I would
like to see it so I don't know yet I've
seen the trailer the the trailer was
very interesting and it's going to kind
of change people's perceptions of of the
history of
India so I would like to see it I hear
it is good but I haven't seen it yet so
maybe I'll see it hopefully this week
and in the next episode I can perhaps
give you my feedback about
it
okay
RIT Das says is the US governed by a
certain group of Institution for example
the military Etc the US is governed by
an invisible
entity which is not part of of any one
institution so I say this because Biden
is not ruling the country and Kamala
Harris is not ruling the country but
clearly somebody is so it would most
likely be the likelihood is high that it
would be the forign EST the the the the
state department establishment the
foreign the foreign establishment the
military industrial complex and the
various
oligarchs
who uh you find in the US the the top
billion and all that it would be a
coalition of these people maybe somebody
else rules them we don't know one can
only speculate so that's what I can
say gaming lover says why did
I don't know how many million years ago
I think five four five million years
ago so about around maybe 10 okay I
don't remember the exact timeline you
can look it up if you are interested but
at a certain point in time not that long
ago our ancestors were the same as the
ancestors of the chimpanzees and the
gorillas and the other apes and then
because of geographical distribution
each of the branches evolved separately
let me go back to the map where's the
map here the map one
second so the best data the best
evidence that we have points to the fact
that Humanity evolved in Africa if new
evidence comes up I will revise my
opinion but based on what we have today
the best evidence that we have says that
Humanity evolved in Africa there is
something called The Rift Valley in in
Eastern
Africa and what probably happened is
that different species of different
groups of our ancestors common ancestor
with all these Apes they were isolated
on two different regions in Africa and
over a couple of million years ago
because there was no interaction between
these two groups that were permanently
divided they evolved differently and in
in the past uh the number of humans or
or ancestors was quite low and they
would travel and they would get isolated
from each other maybe sometimes
permanently and that's how they evolv
differently over a few lack years few
million years and they all appeared as
different species
eventually so some became gorillas some
became chimpanzees some became bonobos
some Gibbons some orangutans and so on
so forth and some humans here we are and
we are the most intelligent of the Apes
the most evolved evolved in
intellectually of the Apes physically we
are the weakest of the Apes a chimpanzee
is way shorter than a human being but
way stronger than a human being
and don't even talk about gorillas how
strong they are so physically we are the
weakest of the Apes but this is what has
set us apart and that's why we have
evolved so far so nobody has stopped
evolving everybody is evolving all the
time but evolution takes a very long
time to become
apparent so if you look at humans that
would have existed a 100,000 years
before today they would have probably
looked very much like us there could be
superficial minor changes minor cosmetic
differences but overall they would have
been very much like us so the oldest
evidence of hom Homo sapiens is 400,000
years ago in North Africa jbel
Hood so those were anatomically modern
Homo sapiens for almost half a million
years ago so that's how slow evolution
is so nobody has stopped evolving we
evolved all evolved differently just
like the cats there are so many
different species of cats
there are so many different species of
butterflies there are so many different
species of uh well not the dogs there
are breeds of dogs but and and the dog
is a subspecies of the wolf of course
but yeah if you look at the wolf and the
bear you can see some similarity in the
face the face is similar right the wolf
and the bear so there is some they will
have a common ancestor for sure
including and they would have a common
and with the Veals as well so evolution
is very interesting but nobody has
stopped
evolving
okay okay what happened here okay mayang
Kumar goam says who is the better PM
atal G or Modi
G you asking a difficult question I will
say Modi
G okay what else okay we have cross two
hours I should end this
now uh rudra notal hello sir hello hello
let's take maybe one more
question let's take one more
question okay when will the next
elephant Evolution take place everything
is evolving every species is evolving
but the like I just said Evolution
becomes apparent only over very long
periods of time so let's say you are
reborn 100 ,000 years from now you will
see probably see a slightly different
kind of elephant at that
time okay
um
okay yush says how to study history
geopolitics and present scenarios
together look studying anything properly
takes time I understand geopolitics
because I've studied hisory history
world history for since since I was a
child probably since I was seven or
eight years old I was interested in
history and I used to study history from
not your school textbooks which are
horrifically boring but other books and
I've done that for a long time that's
how I UND that's how I have an
understanding of geopolitics because
geopolitics is all about the same
patterns that you see across history so
how do you study it together you read
read read read read read read in your
spare time read in your free time find
whatever book you can find and
read and read indiscriminately read any
book that you find and then hopefully if
you do that over five years 10 years you
will gain a reasonably good
understanding of the subject or you
could take my course on on geopolitics
which will give you a very quick start
on geopolitics it'll explain the
fundamental principles of geopolitics in
one single 4-Hour session so if you're
interested the link is in the
description below ac. University okay
let's take one final
question isan says how do you see the
future of Western response to indic
Technologies and knowledge that were
before ignored as India Rises um in I'm
not sure what indic technologies
are IND knowledge Indian knowledge I
understand we we have see we had ancient
science and all which was all taken to
the west by the Arabs by the Persians by
the Arabs mainly and today's sign and
technology is built on those
foundations uh we had our own philosophy
our own historical records which are all
burned down and all but technology look
during the Saras Sindu phase we had
extremely advanced technology ship
building Hydro Engineering and all that
uh we were the inventors of
uh of seric Steel which is now called
Damascus steel it used to come out of
India Crucible steel to half thousand
years ago at least Southern India Tamil
Nadu Sri Lanka Etc uh and we have in the
past had lots of technologies that
emerge out of India today what indic
technologies are I don't know today we
seek to import Western
Technologies uh and we seek to yeah
that's what it is so that's the
situation there are no secret
technologies that we have in India today
that are superior to today's Western
Technologies so that is just the the
truth the factual truths of the
matter cash Dynamo says what degree do
you need to become a theoretical
physicist see a theoretical physicist is
somebody who does active research in the
unsolved problems of the universe and
for that you need funding you cannot be
jobless and be doing active research
because who's going to pay for your
meals you need an income right so a
theoretical physicist first of all needs
to understand theoretical physics and
the mathematics behind it and needs to
have a job in a research institution or
a university for that you need a degree
of a
PhD you can have a master's degree and
do it too but uh for a job in a research
institution of a certain caliber they
would require a PhD
in in a branch of
physics typically something like
theoretical physics also it could be an
Allied branch subsidiary branch but that
that is fine so typically to be a
theoretical physicist you would need at
least a master's degree ideally a PhD
and you would need employment in a in an
organization that allows you to do
research maybe a few hours a week that's
how you become a theoretical physicist
all right all right all right all right
U shall I take one last
question shall I take one last
question
um
sidar Singh rajur says if Mahabharat was
real how would you place it in the
timeline with respect to the indust valy
civilization the sarasti Hindu phase of
India's history probably Mahabharat
could have been contemporaneous with
that maybe with the early part of that
of that thing so if the Mahabharat
happened let's say hypothetically 5,000
years ago then that was in the middle of
the sarasti Hindu phase or what you call
the Indus Valley phase of India's
history so if so the Mahabharat probably
was
contemporaneous with the uh sarasti
Hindu phase of Indian history maybe the
early phase or maybe the slightly more
mature
phase so yeah that's how it probably
would be but that depends on when the
Mahabharat happened it probably happened
around five 5,000 or so years before
today most likely but we still don't
know for sure so that's how I would
place it all right with that question
with that answer we are at the end of
today's session thank you so very much
once again for all the questions I
apologize once again to all those of you
whose questions I could not take I'll do
more of these as always and we'll take
more questions and hopefully everybody
gets to get an answer for me all right
so until then thank you very much once
again for your viewership for watching
for your support for your for everything
and I will see you very soon in the next
episode probably this weekend until then
take care have a good night good day
wherever you are and keep raising your
your standards do something that you're
proud of thank you bye